Stanford University the last time we
discussed both the classical I think and
the quantum mechanical description of
harmonic oscillators and we found
classically that every harmonic
oscillator has an energy which is
independent of its frequency and equal
to the temperature in thermal
equilibrium we calculated the partition
function and we calculated the average
energy of any harmonic oscillator and
found out that the energy was just equal
to T when I say T will be the textbook
KT equals what I call temperature
alright that's a that's a true statement
it led to this puzzle about molecules
which have little oscillators how come
in at very low temperatures also the the
molecules don't exhibit this energy
because it's not there
we know that that the molecule will not
exhibit the internal energy at very low
temperatures and we found out that the
answer had to do with quantum mechanics
instead of the energy being equal to T
in quantum mechanics we found out or
let's let's just go through it I'll go
through it very briefly some points here
that are worth emphasizing the energy
levels of the quantum mechanical
oscillator are e sub n equals H bar
Omega n we can drop this ground state
energy it's not important or put it in
it doesn't matter it will make any
difference to anything incidentally
there's an interesting point here the
uncertainty principle is a correct
principle but you can think of it a
little more broadly any given quantum
state you always corresponds
now I'm using the word correspond Leslie
and I'm not going to tell you precisely
what it means but it corresponds to a
little patch in phase space X and P it
corresponds to little patch in space
space where the area of that patch is
equal the Planck's constant and maybe
it's plunks constant / - I don't
remember offhand and it's not a question
of greater than or equal to it is equal
any given quantum state to a patch of
size H bar area in the phase space equal
to H bar now if the area is a little
circle that's sort of the most tightly
knit the kind of quantum state then a
little circle in phase space then
clearly Delta X and Delta P will be
equal to each other and Delta X Delta P
will equal H bar will be proportional to
H bar if the size of this of the area of
this circle is of order H bar and I'll
use the term of order of order H bar
then if we take a nice little symmetric
disk like this then Delta x times Delta
P will be equal to H bar there are the
quantum states which have the same area
which might look like ellipse ellipses
again for an ellipse like this if Delta
x times Delta P is equal to H bar or
lower if the sorry if the area of this
patch is equal to H bar then again Delta
x times Delta P will be equal to H bar
but then there are much more peculiar
States there are States quantum states
which correspond to the area H bar but
which are spread out in some other kind
of way like that
the properties of the quantum state can
be identified with a patch of phase
space whose area is equal to H bar but
it's quite apparent for this kind of
configuration the sneaky kind of
configuration this area is H bar that
Delta P times Delta X is really greater
than H bar Delta P means the spread and
momentum Delta X means the spread in X
and if you don't keep the configuration
tightly knit into some circle or ellipse
or rectangle or something like that but
let it get spread out into this kind of
snakey configuration then you can take a
quantum state which occupies area H bar
and nevertheless make it have Delta X
and Delta P such that the product is
greater than H bar so it's kind of
interesting and I'm going to give you an
example now an example where this is
useful in thinking it's the harmonic
oscillator let's just take the
Hamiltonian to be P squared plus x
squared over 2 I don't want to introduce
any constants into here it just makes it
simpler and the ground state the ground
state is this wave function or this
probability distribution which is
concentrated at the center and it has an
area H bar Delta x times Delta P is H
bar now what about then the first
excited state the first excited state if
you think about a harmonic oscillator
harmonic oscillators oscillate and they
oscillate in both momentum and position
and if you think about the way the phase
point moves in phase space classically
it moves in circles when the circle is
projected onto the horizontal axis you
have the ordinary oscillation of
position when it's projected onto the
vertical axis you have the oscillation
of the velocity or the
intim the next excited state represents
a harmonic oscillator with a little bit
of increased energy moving around in a
semi-classical and approximate classical
description in the circle and so it
occupies a little ring of phase space
but how big is that ring or how thick is
that ring that ring must be such that
the area is again equal to H bar the
next excited state is another ring of
area h bar as you move out as you move
out the width since the total area of
each state is equal to h bar as you move
out further and further the thickness or
the thickness of the annular ring
describing each quantum state does get
thinner and thinner but the area stays
the same ah what's the radius of the nth
circle here anybody figure that out if
we take the nth circle what what now NH
bar yeah NH bar is the area of the
energy weight H bar is the area of the
circle of the of the annular ring okay
yep well I'll tell you what the answer
is the answer I believe is the square
root of n is the is the radius of the
circle the square root of n okay so the
radius of the circle here is the square
root of n the square root of the of the
nth circle just fitting them together
yeah question the question this pie R
squares but there again now we're just
talking about we're talking about the
radius of an annular ring the nth
annular ring such that each one butts up
against the next one and gives you a
disc of area in the area this in such
we're talking about the entering each
one has area H bar so what is the area
of the whole disc here the whole area of
the whole disc is proportional to n but
the area of the annular ring right a
little it's okay let's do it the area of
the whole disc is n so the area n times
H bar I just want to figure out whether
it's n to the one half and to the three
quarters what it is the area of the
whole thing is in yes times H bar R
that's the area of the whole thing and
that's equal to PI R squared where R is
the radius of this disc in phase space
right PI R squared all right so that
tells us that n h-bar over PI the square
root is equal to R now what what does
that mean about the or that does it
doesn't it that tells us that the radius
of the annular ring
here the enth annular ring is
proportional to the square root of n
that's important it's proportional to
the square root of n in fact it's
proportional to the square root of n
times H bar now what is this radius if
you look at this formula over here you
see that this radius of the square of
the radius that is essentially the
energy the square of the radius we can
think of this as R squared and it is
just the energy apart from a factor of 2
R being loose with factors of 2 and even
with path factors of Pi so P squared
plus x squared is the energy and that's
equal to R squared R is of order n H bar
so that means that the energy is of
order no no no no no no R squared R
squared is just a border and H bar so
the quantization of energy can be just
thought of as the uncertainty principle
for the case of the harmonic oscillator
but the uncertainty principle not
thought of as Delta e Delta P greater
than H bar but a different kind of
uncertainty principle which tells you
that every quantum state occupies a
little region of phase space which is of
order H bar an area but that doesn't
mean that the shape has to be a little
circle in this case the shape is annular
rings the uncertainty of these excited
LP x times Delta P of these excited
States is much bigger than H bar if I
take this in excited state here and ask
what is its Delta X and its Delta P
they're this big
and that big and it's much bigger than H
bar so that's a that's a useful way to
think about quantum mechanics the
quantum states are to be identified as
patches of phase space whose area is H
bar each one of these is a unique
quantum state distinguishable
discreet and so in any one of these
states no matter how big Delta X and
Delta P get every single one of them is
a unique definite quantum state and if
you know that the system is in that
discrete quantum state then the
probability distribution in quantum
states is just look localized at one
unique quantum state and the entropy is
zero okay ah and thermal equilibrium of
course these different rings have
different have a probability
distribution and it's the Boltzmann
distribution and the entropy is whatever
it is all right so I got sidetracked
into an interesting discussion but let's
go back to the classical and the quantum
mechanical harmonic oscillator the
classical harmonic oscillator up in the
left hand corner has energy e equals T
the quantum mechanical oscillator did we
write down the answer ok let's write
down the answer the energy of the
quantum mechanical oscillator is Omega H
bar oh let's let's just go through again
where it came from very quickly we
calculated the partition function the
partition function came from summing up
over all the quantum states which means
summing up over all those annular rings
e to the minus baby start with a
partition function e to the minus beta
times the energy of the nth level which
is h-bar Omega times n that's a
geometric sum and just very quickly go
through it sum that's equal to 1 over 1
minus e to the minus beta H bar Omega or
equal to e to the that's good enough
that's that's that's good way to express
it
ok and then from that we can calculate
the energy of the oscillator this is Z
log Z we can calculate log Z is just the
logarithm of this and we can calculate
the derivative of minus log Z with
respect the beta that's the energy
average energy of course of the
oscillator and that's equal to Omega
h-bar divided by e to the beta Omega H
bar minus one the one coming from the
one the suet what it is all right so
that's the energy and if you look at it
and stare at it for a minute you realize
that at high temperature when beta is
small when beta is small we can expand
this exponential it becomes 1 plus beta
Omega H bar in the denominator minus 1
Omega H bar and 1 minus 1 cancels Omega
H bar cancels and the answer is 1 over
beta which is temperature so at high
temperatures we reproduce the classical
physics but at low temperature when beta
is very large when temperatures are low
beta is large this exponent is exponent
here is very large you can forget the 1
and the energy is just Omega H bar over
e to the beta Omega H bar and that's
extremely small when beta is large
temperature is small the energy is
tremendously suppressed compared to the
classical answer so that's the solution
if you like of the puzzle of what
happens to the the ah
classical energy stored in at very very
low temperatures it's much less than you
would have gotten from classical physics
at high temperatures are the same at low
temperatures it's very hard to excite
the oscillations basically alright one
other thing the inn which appears here
we can just define by definition we will
call it the number of quanta in that
oscillator we'll think of the oscillator
as having an occupation number whatever
that means
just definition the occupation number of
the harmonic oscillator is just which of
these rings you're on or which quantum
state in the sense of how many units of
energy does the quantum state have units
of energy in units of h-bar Omega so
that's a few like a definition of the
number of quanta are in that oscillation
the next thing we're going to come to is
black body radiation blackbody radiation
is a historical of enormous historical
importance of course it's also of a
importance in many many other ways
besides history but it has a glorious
history and being the origin of quantum
mechanics or the historical yeah which
the the classical result energy to the
texture yes yes but it wasn't it wasn't
um it was funny was it I mean it could
have been interpreted as a need for
other physics okay the answer is I don't
know the degree to which people actually
are worried about that about the
molecular you talk about the molecular
internal motions I'm quite certain that
they did worry about it but remember
that they knew very little about
molecules at that time and the whole
idea of molecules had yet to be really
established so my own guess is that yes
they knew about it they worried about it
but it wasn't in the front burner the
way that the blackbody radiation was
radiation they thought they knew
everything about wave theory electric
and magnetic fields they thought they
really understood electromagnetism and
the puzzle which was very similar a very
very similar type was that a box of
radiation by a box of radiation I mean
we take some cavity I guess we would
call it with reflecting walls now of
course we don't have perfectly
reflecting walls it doesn't matter much
in fact it's even better if they're not
perfectly reflecting but they allow they
transmit some energy through them then
we can say that whatever's in the box
will come through the thermal
equilibrium on the outside with the
outside a given temperature but what can
be in the box radiation can be in the
box
radiation bouncing back and forth waves
of radiation bouncing back and forth
radiation of different wavelengths now
it was known
from very early times early times from
from Maxwell theory and so forth that
the radiation inside a box could be
thought of as a collection of harmonic
oscillators in the same sense that a
vibrating guitar string I was mean to
bring my guitar in for this purpose but
the of like a vibrating guitar string or
can also be thought of as a system of
harmonic oscillators not a single
harmonic oscillator hey that's pretty
good
not a single harmonic oscillator but it
can vibrate in any one of its whoo yeah
yeah you get a point this is the first
mode of oscillation and that's a
harmonic oscillator completely
independent of that the system can
vibrate in its second mode now I'm not
going to try to make that well yeah yeah
clue third mode there's a third mode and
so forth and each one of these
oscillations are separate and the system
is described by a collection of harmonic
oscillations each harmonic oscillation
and this was not an invention of
Einstein or this goes back to probably
original wave theory everything we knew
about wave theories not everything we
knew everything they knew about wave
theory that waves could be described as
collections of oscillators and in
thermal equilibrium each oscillator
ought according to classical
thermodynamics have an energy equal the
KT but there's an infinite number of
possible modes of oscillation I could
only exhibit the handful because I'm not
clever enough to make this thing
oscillate in arbitrarily short
wavelengths but there was no reason to
believe that there was any cutoff in how
short wavelengths could be there isn't
cut off on how long wavelengths can be
inside a box it doesn't make sense to
think about a wave longer in wavelength
in the size of the box
or another way of saying it is if you
have a guitar string of a certain length
there are not going to be waves of
longer wavelength on that guitar string
than the distance between the endpoints
of the string but they can be
arbitrarily short wavelengths now of
course for a real guitar string it has a
certain thickness and there comes a
point where you can't really make it
oscillate with very very short
wavelengths in particular it doesn't
make any sense to think about wave
length shorter than the inter molecular
spacing along the the so for a guitar
string is a natural cutoff but for
radiation nobody knew any reason why
there should be a smallest wave length
and if not then in thermal equilibrium
every single wavelength should have the
same energy KT and the damn thing should
have an infinite explosive amount of
energy simply because there's an
infinite number of possible ways you can
oscillate of course most of these
wavelengths would be very very high
frequency but nevertheless thermal
equilibrium should populate them the
same way the thermal Akula lot of
thermal equilibrium should have
populated the oscillations of a very
stiff molecule it should also have
stiff string for example a very high
frequency oscillations so that was the
real puzzle and people knew enough about
about electromagnetism that they had
confidence in the theory and the theory
was failing I was sailing because it was
an observed fact that the radiation
inside a box was not infinite in energy
in fact if you looked at the radiation
that was in the Box you would discover
in fact that there was a cut-off in its
wavelength the cutoff in other words a
shortest wavelength that the Box could
oscillate at so you might have said okay
that just means
that physics has some smallest length
all right we didn't expect that
something new something entirely new but
still it can be made to coexist with
basic classical physics if Roberto said
there was a smallest length but it
doesn't work that way the smallest
length wave oscillation that's present
in the thermal equilibrium of a box of
radiation that smallest wavelength
depends on temperature how can the
shortest distance in the world depend on
the temperature that doesn't make sense
so when a box of radiation was
considered and studied and you know how
did they do this they let a little bit
of radiation out and study the spectral
decomposition of it at each temperature
there was a shortest wavelength or
approximately a shortest wavelength but
that shortest wavelength depended on
something that it didn't make sense that
depended on the temperature itself that
was a puzzle the solution of the puzzle
was simply the quantum mechanics of
these harmonic oscillations so I want to
go through that and show you the show
you the basic theory of the harmonic
oscillation and we'll work out the
stefan-boltzmann law or one version one
particular version of the
stefan-boltzmann law the
stefan-boltzmann law applied to the
energy density of radiation blackbody
radiation we're talking about blackbody
radiation okay any any questions before
I begin this the derivation of the
energy in blackbody radiation
yeah
seems like the minimum wavelength to be
actually the weight next get cleaned up
besides right now why shouldn't my wife
all know in thermal equilibrium
everything gets populated everything
gets populated that can get populated
and there's no there's no reason why an
atom cannot in principle or why now why
an atom cannot excite the modes of
oscillation of yet shorter wavelength it
might take a long time it might take a
long time to populate atoms of a certain
size aren't readily going to convert you
know I'll tell you it can happen how can
an atom of how can an atom create a high
frequency photon okay well one simple
way that can create a high frequency
photon we haven't talked about photons
yet but let's talk about photons one way
that it can do it is to absorb several
simultaneously several low frequency
photons and then re-emit the energy is
one high frequency photon so it can
happen it's one of the possible
processes that can happen that an atom
can it's a nonlinear process the
frequency of the radiation changes but
but a whole bunch of photons come
together you can think of it as
accidentally excite the atom and the
atom then D excites and gives back a
very high for a frequency photon just or
scatters just scatters a lot of low
frequency photons and creates a high
frequency Photon
they say that's very improbable and
you're right that means that it would
take a long amount of time for the
system to come to thermal equilibrium
and that's true that classically it
would take a long time for the system to
come to thermal equilibrium but when it
did come to thermal equilibrium it would
have this odd property of having
every mode filled with energy an
infinite amount of energy and that that
was intolerable but let me say it
another way at low temperatures the
cutoff was the cutoff in wavelengths was
much longer than the size of an atom so
it didn't make sense to just say atomic
diameters cut off things it depended on
the temperature at low temperatures only
very long wavelengths were present as
the temperature went up shorter and
shorter wavelengths become important and
this just didn't jibe with anything that
anybody knew I mean it was it was a real
crisis ah
plunk had an idea and the idea didn't
really make a lot of sense I will just
tell you very briefly that's one of
these things that made sufficiently
little sense that I can't even reproduce
what the idea what the argument was it
was Einstein of course who really got
the argument right
uh what Planck said is that the walls of
the container are filled with atoms
atoms emit radiation and for reasons he
didn't know but reasons that didn't seem
all that incredibly revolutionary the
oscillators in the walls oscillate only
with very definite frequencies all right
and he said the energy of an oscillator
he spoke about oscillators in the walls
of the system meaning atoms but again
remember this was 1900 ad UM's still
hadn't been identified and still were
not understood
so plunk said for reasons unknown the
frequency of oscillations of atoms the
atoms even oscillate not all atoms
oscillate that mean they do oscillate
but they don't oscillate as harmonic
oscillators but his idea was atoms
oscillate like harmonic oscillators and
each harmonic oscillator atom has a
frequency Omega and he said the energy
of
the atoms or the oscillators in the wall
satisfied that the energy is equal to an
integer multiple of the frequency times
a new constant which he called I don't
think he called Planck's constant he
called that H equals H bar or H H bar
came a little bit later H nu equals H
bar Omega and through some kind of
mumbo-jumbo that I've never completely
understood this was supposed to explain
the fact that that the radiation in the
box was cut off at some highest
wavelength this is not the right
explanation although the formula that he
concocted out of this was correct the
formula he concocted for the amount of
radiation in each oscillator was correct
in each in each oscillation of the
electromagnetic field the real truth was
that the quantization of energy levels
was not the quantization of energy
levels of the atoms in the walls of the
box it was the quantization of the
energy levels of the radiation itself
inside the box in other words the
radiation was made out of discrete
quanta of energy where every frequency
of possible oscillation would have an
integer number of quanta and the energy
of each possible oscillation would be
some integer times H bar times the
frequency of that oscillator these
things are called quanta now which just
correspond to the amount of energy in
each one of these oscillations that to
be called photons
Einstein knew very well that he was
talking about some kind of particulate
theory of radiation and he was saying
something extremely radical extremely
extraordinarily radical in fact you know
when you think about it he was this
young man who was completely unknown
nobody had ever heard of him
all these famous physicists and this
young man out of nowhere out of the
Patent Office in 1905 said you know
everybody who has ever thought about
radiation and electromagnetic radiation
had it completely wrong
all you people were wrong
electromagnetic radiation comes in some
sort of particles now it was not because
he didn't understand that that the wave
theory of radiation was very effective
he just somehow had an inner sense that
it was the radiation here which was
quantized and not the oscillations of
the wall nobody believed them
incidentally it took about 20 years
before people really believed there were
photons even this not the it was a long
time but having told you the history
let's go through the mathematics this is
not what Einstein did Einstein didn't
have the mathematics to do this he
didn't do it the way I'm doing it he did
it using lots of thermodynamics and lots
of clever insight but we can do it
really mathematically and very cleanly
all I want to do is calculate the total
amount of energy in this box of
radiation so to do so we have to state
more clearly the nature of these
oscillators not the ones in the walls of
the box but the oscillations in the
radiation field which are very much like
the oscillations of a guitar string in
particular if the walls of the box are
reflecting that implies that the
electric field at the boundaries of the
box is zero take that take that is given
that the electric field at the
boundaries of the box is zero and that's
analogous to the guitar string where the
the deviation of the guitar string from
equilibrium is zero at the boundary of
the string all right electric field can
be thought of as sort of a height of the
of the oscillation here and so the
guitar string is
constrained to be a patched to have zero
oscillation at the ends of the guitar
string same thing for the
electromagnetic field for the electric
field so let's think about an electric
wave propagating along the x axis here
what yeah yeah but actually that doesn't
make any difference at all if you deep
inside the box if you there are some
surface effect to the boundaries of the
box that wouldn't mean it there would be
a lot of different frequency meaning
like it having a whole lot of different
drivers guitar strings no no no what is
true you're asking if you were to expand
the box a little bit you would say the
frequencies would be a little bit
different than if you would shrink it a
little bit there would be a little
different yeah yeah what you have to do
is you have to read you you don't just
add those things together you can't add
the oscillations of one theory of the
guitar string to the oscillations of
another theory for example you could you
could have instead of fixed boundary
conditions here in the guitar string
here's another kind of guitar string
it's not a real guitar string you have a
pole and another pole over here polled I
mean literally a like a ball and you
have a ring around this pole and a ring
around this pole and the guitar string
is connected to the Rings the Rings can
move up and down now they're not
confined to be attached to fixed
positions and this is entirely different
kind of waves that waves that now can
exist are such that they don't have to
vanish at the endpoints something else
has to be true namely the derivative has
to be equal to zero at that point but
it's a difference simply a different
system well
this system if you worked it out would
give you exactly the same answer for the
thermodynamics of the guitar string when
they when the whole system got large the
end effects are not important the end
effects turn out not to be important
that you have to probe have to work that
out you don't add the oscillations of
this theory to the oscillations of this
theory they're just two different
theories now another possibility is you
could have flexion at the end of the
walls here friction would lead to yet a
different description of what goes on on
the guitar string but all of them would
lead to the same thermodynamic behavior
of the of the other guitar string so
it's sufficient just to study one
particular case and far from the
endpoints the answers don't depend on
the details of the boundary conditions I
agree that has to be proved that's not
obvious but it's true so let's consider
the waves that can exist on a finite
string of length L if they have to be if
they have to be if they have to vanish
if the height of this wave let's call
the height of the wave here let's call
it X now let's not call it X let's call
it capital y and it's a function of
position it's a function of X and a
given wave has to have the form sine 2
pi naught sine pi PI over L x times n
what is in now in is the number of well
the number of oscillations number of
half oscillations this would correspond
to N equals 1 this would correspond to N
equals 2 and so forth let me call it M
I'm going to get I don't want to call it
in because I've used n for something
else I've used in for the number of
quanta in the oscillation this has
nothing to do with the number of
oscillator of Kwan
in the oscillator it just has to do with
how many nodes there are in a particular
electromagnetic wave it's a completely
classical concept and it's just the kind
of sine waves that can fit onto an
interval of length L all of these sine
waves okay let's let's let's just look
at it if X if M is equal to 1 then this
just becomes sine PI over L X but what
is X at the other end X starts at 0 over
here and X is equal to L over here at x
equals 0 the sine of 0 is 0 and at x
equals L the sine of pi is 0 so this
wave fits into the box
with proper boundary conditions at the
end any integer here will work so there
are an infinite number of patterns of
oscillation characterized by the sine
waves but the sine waves each one of
them has an amplitude a amplitude of
oscillation which means the magnitude of
the oscillation of each one of these and
so you'll have to put a coefficient in
front of it why let's call it sub m and
it's just a number for each oscillation
but it's time-dependent it oscillate the
oscillator oscillates up and down or the
let's take this case here and oscillates
up and down and that corresponds to why
oscillating Y is an oscillator Y is a
function of time and it is an oscillator
it's a harmonic oscillator so these are
the Aqsa laters here and in general you
can write that Y of X is a sum of M of Y
sub M sine M PI over L
X these are the dynamical degrees of
freedom think of this as a function of
time Y is also a function of time and
these are the things that oscillate
these are just fixed functions so the
system is a system of harmonic
oscillators and the next question is
what is the frequency of each oscillator
the answer depends on the velocity of
propagation of the waves there's a
relationship between em and the and the
frequency of oscillation oscillation and
I'll tell you what it is let's write
this in another way another useful way
let's write this as Y of M sign case KX
m pi over l I have called K that's a
standard terminology M PI over L is
called K and K is called the wave number
it's called the wave number its itself
not necessarily an integer but if you
know m then you know K what's the
connection between the frequency and K
the larger K is the shorter the
wavelength that's large K this is low K
shorter the wavelength the higher the
frequency I'll tell you what the
relationship is the frequency is equal
to the velocity of propagation let's
call it C times K the higher K the
larger K the higher the frequency and
they're just related by this velocity of
propagation of waves the light C is of
course the speed of light all right so
let's let's
summarize then a given wave given
wave-like motion has is parametrized by
an M it has a frequency which is equal
to C times K which is the same as C
times M PI over L each one of these
oscillations stores energy independently
of all the others and classically each
one of them would store the same amount
of energy and the whole thing would have
an infinite amount of energy now what
about now here I'm talking about
one-dimensional waves
what about three dimensional waves three
dimensional waves you do almost exactly
the same thing let's write the general
pattern for three-dimensional waves
we're not now talking about the height
of a string we could be talking about a
wave field such as the electric or
magnetic field and a light wave but
let's just let's not call it electric
well we can call it electric field now
let's just call it f it could be
electric field it could be magnetic
field or it could be some other wave
field gravitation well no that's not
there let's not get into quantum gravity
today the electrical magnetic field and
it is also a sum over different
independent oscillators now the wave
pattern involves all three dimensions
and the general wave that can propagate
in a box in three dimensions with
boundary conditions on the walls that it
should be zero looks similar to this
except it has three factors it has a
sine or we can write it in several ways
n sub X let's see a PI over L times X
it's a product times sine M sub y PI
over L
x y x sine of M sub Z PI over L times Z
these are the three dimensions of space
and M x and y n MZ
are integers three integers a given wave
has to fit into the Box horizontally it
has to fit into the Box vertically and
has to fit into the Box in the other
direction and that's ensured by this
form here and then there's a coefficient
which depends on time which can be
labeled Y of a y sub M meaning Y of M X
and y MZ we can also write this oh and
this is a sum of course we sum over all
possible modes in the box and of course
this is nothing but Fourier analysis in
a box there's nothing done nothing
special here we can also write this as a
sum of Y and use a different notation
sine KX times X sine K Y times y sine KZ
times Z where the relationship between
are the KS and the M's is exactly as it
was before K sub X is equal to M sub X
pi case of Y is equal to L over L and so
forth all right this is the pattern of
oscillation of a general electromagnetic
wave inside a cavity with Y being the
thing that oscillates the point is that
there is one harmonic oscillator for
each way of choosing m x and y and MZ
and we have to add together all of their
energies once we know once we know how
to label
oscillators and we know how many of them
there are then this is the way of
keeping track of how many different
oscillators there are one more thing we
need to know we need to know the
frequency of an oscillator and the
frequency of an oscillator namely the
oscillator that has wave number K X KY
and K Z is just equal to K the magnitude
of K square root of KX square plus KY
square plus KZ squared times C equals
the square root K x squared plus K Y
squared plus KZ squared times C just the
magnitude of the wave vector magnitude
of the wave number times the speed of
light that's its frequency so now we
have laid out for us all of the harmonic
oscillators we've labeled them label
them by three integers we know the
frequency of each one we could write it
in terms of the MS if we like and we can
ask how much energy is stored in this
whole thing classically it's quite
infinite it's quite infinite because
each oscillator has the same amount of
energy quantum mechanically the answer
is different let's sum it all up let's
do it let's really get into it get into
the thing and calculate how much energy
is in this oscillating box of radiation
at a temperature T the temperature T
where does that come from well the box
of gas the box of photons or box of
radiation could be sitting on somebody
stove that's all it's just heated up by
whatever means it's heated up by the
walls of the box become hot
they emit radiation they absorb
radiation the radiation comes into
thermal equilibrium with the walls of
the box which have been heated to some
temperature how by emission and
absorption of radiation which of course
is emission and absorption of the quanta
of the oscillators here photons
okay that's that's all theory and let's
see if we can work it out now
the energy let's write down the energy
stored in the wave which is
characterized by a given wave number K
wave number means a set of three wave
numbers kxky and kz or NX m xml my n MZ
all right that's equal to now we go back
to the theory of harmonic oscillators it
is Omega h-bar divided by e to the beta
Omega H bar minus 1 that was the formula
for the harmonic oscillator energy as a
function of frequency and as a function
of temperature that's the energy of a
given oscillator and we can write that
in another way our Omega is K the
magnitude of K times the speed of light
H bar divided by e to the beta K see
let's see yeah H bar
are in this formula here k is the same
thing as the magnitude of K I don't want
to try to stick too many symbols into
this exponent minus one excuse me
I've just rewritten the fact that Omega
is equal to KC H bar but nothing else
that's the energy of the oscillator with
wave number K how much energy is there
altogether we've got to add up all the
oscillators so the total energy is equal
to the sum over all of the possible
modes of oscillation that means sum of
MX my and MZ k CH bar divided by e to
the beta K C H bar minus one it's a big
sum any questions up till now
all right the carry on we're going to
approximate the sum by an integral the
point is that let's let's look at this
here K is M PI over L imagine the box is
very big L is large large now means
large by comparison with a way over
there wavelengths of our light in there
if L is large the difference between
neighboring values of K is small
neighboring K values of K mean
neighboring values of the wave number m
right what's the difference between
neighboring adjacent values of K X let's
call it Delta K X the difference is just
PI over L in other words if we change em
by one unit
K changes by PI over L when L is large
this change in K is small so if we think
of this as a sum naught over m but as
the sum over the value
of k then with summing up a large number
of numbers each of which is a function
of K and the k's are very very closely
separated very very dense here's a
function of K it's got K in the
numerator and it's got this stuff in the
denominator and we're adding it all up
and it's just the ideal situation when L
gets large to replace a sum by an
integral so let's do that we're going to
replace this by an integral over K but
before we do we have to remember that
integrals and sums are related in a
particular way that involves a factor
that we have to keep track of just
abstractly a sum over integers MX + y +
MZ is going to be replaced by an
integral the KX whips the KX d KY DK z
at the moment I haven't told you what
I'm summing but of course what I'm going
to be something is this but just the
abstract idea of a sum is going to be
replaced by the abstract idea of an
integral but an integral does mean a sum
that's what this Wiggly s means and this
DK x DK y DK Z is just the volume in k
space of the little cells that you're
summing over well each cell has a size
Delta K x equals PI over L Delta KY
equals PI over L and Delta K Z equals PI
over L a simple way to think about it is
d KX d KY DK z integral is replaced by
some the volume element d KX d KY d kz
is replaced by Delta KX Delta K Y Delta
KZ
so we should really write that this is
equal to Delta let's call it Delta three
K which means the product of Delta K X
Delta K Y and Delta K Z that's the way
to replace sums by integrals
you can either approximate an integral
by a sum or approximate a sum by an
integral but you got to keep track of
this factor now what we have here is
just the sum if we want to convert it to
an integral we have to divide by 1 over
Delta K cubed that's the right
prescription the right mathematical
prescription to go from sums to
integrals and so we can write that this
is approximately equal to the integral
the KX de KY let's just call it d 3k
times the same integrand kc h-bar
divided by e to the beta KC H bar minus
1 but we have to put in one of the Delta
K cubed what is that that's L cubed over
PI cubed
l cubed that's interesting that's the
volume of the box not so surprising we
would expect that energy being extensive
or energy being typically proportional
to the house go to F we would expect
that energy is proportional to volume at
a given temperature at a given
temperature here in this calculation is
where the volume comes from happens to
be volume of a pie cubed that number is
there so the first familiar fact is that
the total energy in that box is
proportional to the volume and the rest
of the integral is just the energy
density does it go first of all does it
converge is it finite yeah it's finite
the denominator goes to zero or the
denominator gets big when K gets large
what are we worried about we're worried
about the very short wavelength
oscillations and that means very large K
when K gets large the denominator here
gets big exponentially fast and this
integral is very convergent so the first
second observation is that the total
energy in the box is finite it's
extremely well cut off by this exponent
and there is not an infinite amount of
energy but let's see if we can calculate
it let's see so what do we have let's
calculate it and find the final law of
blackbody radiation for its energy
density in any case L cubed the energy
is equal to L cubed over PI cubed
integral decay I'm not going to write
the integral now I'm going to replace
them gonna change the integration
variable we have e to the beta KC H bar
that's a monstrosity but we can change
variables we're integrating over K
incidentally alright we're integrating
over the three direction three
components of ke and the K that stands
down here is the magnitude of the wave
vector
okay but if I make the change of
variables and let me now change
variables from K namely beta K see H bar
beta C and H bar are just constants let
me call that u and of course there are
three components there's K X this will
give you X and same thing for y and same
thing for Z we're changing variables
from K to you when I do so I just have
to be careful and keep track of it so
let's work it out we have L cubed over
PI cubed what happens to the integral D
cubed K for that we can solve for K K is
equal to u divided by beta C H bar right
so what is decay D u over beta C H bar
so that means it's going to be a d cubed
u the three components of U and there's
going to be downstairs beta C H bar
cubed that can come outside the integral
we'll take it outside the integral in a
moment then we have Omega or we have K C
H bar what is that you over beta the
magnitude of U over beta and we then
have 1 divided by e to the u minus 1
that's it that's the that's the thing
that we have let's take all the
constants and take them on the outside
now that we've now that we've found the
answer or written the answer let's put
all the constants on the outside by
constants I mean the things independent
of you what do we have we have equals L
cubed over PI cubed and then there is
seek
H bar cubed in the denominator and beta
to the fourth beta to the fourth power
downstairs beta from here and three
betas from here and then an integral D
cubed u u of this right you meaningly
the magnitude of u divided by e to the U
minus one this is an integral to
definite integral they're going over
positive values of the three components
of U only positive values why because
the original things that we started with
which were where are they
well the MS the MS were positive
integers so U is positive and the
integral is from zero to infinity for
all three integrals that's it this is a
number I'm gonna tell you know why what
this number is this number is a famous
integral and we'll I'll tell you what
the number is anybody know what the
number is it's PI to the fourth over
fifteen hmm no not quite not that that's
not it's 4 pi times by PI to the 4 4 PI
to the fifth over 15 some such number
some silly number it's a definite
integral right you'll find in tables
it's a three dimensional and to go how
do you make a one dimensional integral
out of this
right spherical coordinates integral 0
to infinity okay go ahead tell me what
to do next for pi right 4 pi 4 PI you
squared that gives you u cubed all
together e to the u minus 1 so there's a
factor of 4 pi out here let's put the 4
pi and it becomes this integral but
that's not quite right you know why it's
not right because this integral would be
integrating it so you you want this
Oracle coordinates alright there are in
three dimensions there are eight octants
eight octants are that you would that
this integral is integrated over but we
only want the octant where all
components of you are positive so
there's a factor of 1/8 not important I
mean there is a factor of 1/8 because
we've over counted but that's it that's
that's the number so let's put the 4 PI
outside this is 1/8 downstairs and then
there is this integral of U cubed over e
to the u minus one famous integral can
be written in terms of Riemann
zeta-function x' and gamma functions and
this and that but it actually has an a
numerical value and it's equal to PI to
the fourth over 15 PI to the fourth over
15 I almost the final answer L cubed for
pi PI to the fourth over 15 I got all
these other things 8 PI cubed C cubed H
bar cubed and finally 1 over beta to the
fourth that's the interesting piece here
1 over beta to the fourth why one of the
to the fourth y is one of a beta to the
fourth interesting because this is T to
the fourth yeah Stefan Boltzmann T to
the fourth T to the fourth power times
some number
oh sorry T to the fourth times L cubed
volume times T to the fourth it's
telling you first of all that the energy
density and thermal radiation is
proportional to T to the fourth the
total amount of energy is finite the
energy density is finite and this
coefficient here is apart from a
numerical factor like a quarter or
something is called a Stefan Boltzmann
factor the Stefan Boltzmann number
constant let's see I want to write it
down correctly Oh anybody know what's
missing is that it's a factor of two
missing and we know where the factor of
two missing is two polarization states
of the photon yeah each each wave vector
each wave vector can support two
distinct orthogonal compa kinds of
oscillations a wave vector going in a
different direction can oscillate
vertically the electric field can
oscillate vertically it can oscillate
horizontally or any ways in between but
in between can be made up out of the
horizontal and the vertical
polarizations so in fact there's another
factor of two no it's just two two two
polarization States that's it not two
cubed okay for each for each direction
there's two possible polarization States
alright all of this is called well it's
it's not quite this step as the standard
Stefan Boltzmann constant that's related
to it by some numerical factor and a
factor of C let's see if I have the
precise formula here
yeah here's the final formula but but
you know the whole story is a long story
the complicated story but it's really
just adding up the quantum mechanical
energy in each harmonic oscillator each
mode of vibration and the important
thing is this exponential downstairs
which really kills off the energy in the
high frequency oscillators yeah
no no well I don't read German so I've
never been I've never tried to read it
yeah oh yeah yeah yeah certainly yeah oh
oh we got the whole formula there but
through what logic is a little bit
unclear quite unclear to me um here's
the final formula e equals volume T to
the fourth and I have PI squared over 15
C cubed H bar cubed which I believe is
also equal to the volume times T to the
fourth times four over C times the thing
which is called the Stefan Boltzmann
constant the Stefan Boltzmann constant
is of course just C over four times this
so this is this is the constant that
appears there number one that agrees
with experiment but that was simply
plunks choice of plugs constant so there
was no great triumph and the numerical
value fitting the stefan-boltzmann
constant but there was something else
that that we've forgot what that sort of
passed by us where is the cutoff in
frequencies that rescues the energy from
being infinite and the answer is
if you go back to the energy stored in
these harmonic oscillators you go from
classical to quantum mechanical in other
words the suppression the suppression
happens at a frequency which is related
to the temperature when h-bar Omega
that's the energy stored in a single
quantum is about equal to the classical
energy that would be in that oscillator
all right we can put in our Boltzmann's
constant if we want the different k k
boltzmann but i'm going to leave it out
when h-bar Omega is about equal to the
temperature when the temperature gets up
to amount a magnitude H Omega that's
when that oscillator starts to begin to
oscillate when the temperature becomes
high enough that oscillator begins to
oscillate another way of saying it is
the cutoff the cutoff in frequencies is
Omega equals the temperature over h-bar
frequencies higher than this the energy
and a single quantum is too high to be
excited so Omega is equal to TL the
h-bar and remember what Omega is omega
is K times C and so the wave number cut
off let's call it cut off cut off is at
ki over h-bar divided by C or is it time
C let's say K Omega is that Omega is K
times C over C so we see another feature
that yes it is as if the short
wavelengths were cut off but not by a
cut-off which is independent of the
temperature the cutoff this corresponds
to a wavelength one over a wavelength of
order T over H bar C when the wavelength
is shorter than this
those oscillators can't also
they have too much energy in a single
quantum too to be able to oscillate and
so we see here that the cutoff is
temperature dependent exactly and what's
more exactly equal to what to what the
experimental cutoff on frequency
frequencies was so this was a great
success
in a sense this was the great success
that the shape of the spectrum was cut
off the classical spectrum was cut off
at wave numbers equal to T over H bar C
do I have that right yeah I do
T of H bar C okay
it was an oscillation well I would just
say the energy of a single quantum is
way above the classical energy so the
classical energy corresponds to a small
fraction of a quantum but you can't
split quanta I think that's the right
way to say zero-point energy is a
constant of course it's there whether
the temperature is zero or the
temperature is anything else right so
there is an infinity in the zero-point
energy
but it's a it's just a constant and so
it doesn't affect adding a constant that
look this is it this is a problem that
the that is plagued physics for a long
time the zero-point quantum mechanical
energy is not zero what does what does
zero-point energy come into since
there's only an additive constant well
it comes in two gravitation energy is
the source of the gravitational field so
the question on the question is why
isn't the vacuum empty space gravitating
and we won't get into that now
well short of that it really has no
implication it's just an additive
constant in the energy of the world that
that doesn't have any effect on energy
differences if you like so that's not to
say that it's not important I mean that
it may be important and it's important
to understand why it doesn't gravitate
but that that's a mystery
yeah that's important right right right
and this has been argued about I think
there was an argument between Dirac and
Polly Polly said why what about this
vacuum energy in Dirac said that
infinite soar can't be there and Polly
said just because it's infinite that
doesn't mean it's zero and so forth and
so on and but but as far as energy
differences goes this is it and that's
good enough
all right um let's yeah developed a mess
agrees
so
and experimental data I don't think
they'd spread yourself I don't think
they'd better than what you mean at that
time a proper probably wasn't better
than five or 10% I don't know these days
these days you can do these things
highly accurately with with with great
accuracy yeah no this is all derived by
having a volume for radiation among coal
also has its distribution can you
explain why I'm a lump coals pretty far
from a box reflecting size a little hole
in it why does the local coal have such
a dispute
thermal equilibrium is thermal
equilibrium if you um yeah I didn't know
do first of all we haven't talked about
emission of radiation we've just talked
about the energy density inside a box
but you're right a lump of coal of
course is just an object which absorbs
and doesn't reflect much energy okay so
if you think if you take the box of
radiation as we've defined it and we put
a lump of coal into it that lump of coal
will absorb and emit radiation that will
absorb and emit radiation are in such a
way as to come to equilibrium it'll be
an equal eventually come to equilibrium
with the thermal radiation there and
that means it will be emitting as much
as it's absorbing so it's emitting as
much as it's absorbing at each
wavelength at each wavelength otherwise
that we get out of the colibri 'm so
it's emitting and absorbing at each
wavelength as there and each wavelength
is being kept in equilibrium and now all
you have to do is suddenly remove the
box remove the reflecting walls and the
lump of coal is emitting but it's not
absorbing because nothing's coming back
it's emitting exactly the way it was
emitting before
but it's no longer absorbing and the
emission should be such that were the
walls there would be the right amount of
emission to the balance and keep the
system in equilibrium but we haven't
talked about emission of radiation from
this box we can that's another subject
what is the connection this was not the
emission of radiation this was the
energy density in the radiation making
us what does this have to do with the
original stefan-boltzmann law the
original stefan-boltzmann law was about
the luminosity at different luminosity
and what has to do with if you take the
box let's see how to think about this
well just take the surface of a hot
region the region could be the box or it
could be the box with a little pinhole
in it
radiation is bouncing off the walls it
has a certain energy density and it
doesn't bounce off the opening here it
just goes out goes out with the speed of
light well let me come to let's come
back to the luminosity later I hadn't
planned to talk about it but we'll talk
about it next time what I did want to
talk about was the pressure in thermal
radiation the pressure is something we
can calculate by straight thermodynamics
and statistical mechanics the
statistical mechanics we've already done
the luminosity is a little bit beyond
what's the thermodynamics can do for the
simple reason that the luminosity is an
out of equilibrium thing it's radiating
because it's out of equilibrium with its
environment so let's let's not do that
now let's so let's come to the pressure
which we can calculate by formulas that
we've already learned just as an example
just as a an example of the
thermodynamic relations and the
statistical mechanical
relations let's see if we can find the
pressure to find the pressure let me
remind you the pressure is equal to
minus the derivative of the free energy
the Helmholtz free energy with respect
to volume at fixed temperature so we
have to calculate the Helmholtz free
energy the Helmholtz free energy a is
equal to minus the temperature times the
logarithm of the partition function so
we have to calculate the partition
function now one way to calculate the
partition function over its logarithm is
to go back to the original oscillators
and you know go all the ways back to the
starting point and calculate Z but
there's an easier way we've already done
most of the work and the easier way is
to use the fact that the energy the
energy is equal to minus the derivative
of log Z with respect to beta you
remember that that was the energy gotten
from the partition function you
calculate the log you take the minus of
it and you differentiate it with respect
to beta and that gives you the energy
well we know the energy we know the
energy in terms of the temperature where
is it let's flow over C Sigma times V T
to the fourth four over Sigma that
doesn't matter
not important over C I think temperature
to the fourth which is 1 over beta to
the fourth equals minus d log Z by D
beta just that's just an ordinary
derivative incidentally I write partial
derivative but it's just the derivative
how do I calculate Z integrate
no the derivative the log Z by D beta is
equal to this then Z let's put the minus
sign here Z is equal to the integral D
beta ya log Z sorry log Z log Z is the
integral D beta of minus 4 Sigma over C
1 over beta to the fourth well we can do
that integral it's just a simple
integral D beta over beta to the fourth
and it's just given by minus 4 Sigma
over C what is what's the integral of 1
over beta to the fourth one-third beta
to the minus 3 yeah 1 over beta cubed
with a 1/3 another minus sign ok
I've lost track of the minus sign when I
do the integral I get a minus sign it
combines with this minus sign I think
and I think yeah all right now we
multiply by T that gives us another 1
over beta that's why I would beta to the
fourth oh I left something out I left
something out of the formula for the
energy the volume another factor of
volume here huh volume volume here
another factor of volume on the outside
another factor of volume ok now we have
the free energy this is equal to minus
AE the derivative of minus a with
respect to volume is the pressure at
fixed temperature so all we have to do
now is differentiate this with respect
to volume that's pretty easy the volume
is just in the numerator here and what
do we find we find that the pressure
has the same numerical coefficient as
the energy density for Sigma over C but
then an extra factor of 1/3 well is T to
the fourth but then an extra factor one
third that one third came from doing the
integral D beta over beta to the fourth
what's the result the result is a
relationship between the pressure and
the energy density is a famous
relationship the pressure is equal to
one third the energy density yi over
volume you remember seeing that anyways
before in cosmology when we studied the
radiation dominated universe we used
pressure is equal to one third the
energy density so this is the famous
relationship between pressure of Aradia
then it's not a general relationship
it's a relationship for radiation for
radiation the pressure is one third the
energy density as I said famous a famous
rule of so that tells you what the force
on a wall on the walls of the box is
okay
um let's see should we stop here and get
questions that went faster than I
thought a would which may mean that I
went too fast in which case we can
collect some questions now or yeah
comments
a molecule counter-rotating and
where you say problem roses head that
thing's broke down the river
your high temperatures classically and
you had to run
the opportunity workout is right is this
replicated all around is a general
puzzle yeah in me yeah I'll give you
another example the specific heat of
solids the specific heat means the
relation between energy and temperature
and so it does have to do with the
energy of solids our whatl solids solids
are crystals I mean real solids good
solids are crystals and they vibrate
they oscillate with crystal lattice
oscillates and so another example of
this is the energy stored in a crystal
lattice again classical mechanics of the
lattice overestimates the energy because
it attributes are a significant energy
to every possible oscillation of this
crystal lattice but most of the
oscillations or many of the oscillations
are too high frequency to so low
temperatures classical mechanics
overestimates the amount of energy
stored in the thermal oscillations or
crystal lattice and you get the wrong
answer but for the specific heat of a so
yeah it doesn't recur over and over
again I'm not sure how many other
examples of it there are what else is
there besides molecules solids I suppose
it also happens in liquids although I
never thought very much about it
radiation molecules what else can you
think of that that oscillates
ideal yes
while thinking specifically about this
issue of energy stored in high frequency
oscillations offhand I can't think of
any other but I'm sure there are yeah
what when it's all about that melts with
pressure all these things and energy
does that mean anybody goes up a lot
during that yeah yeah the energy the
entropy let's go up a lot because all of
a sudden the molecules are no longer
locked in place
and they're sort of moving randomly
through the right certainly the entropy
does go up there's another interesting
thing you can calculate the entropy well
you can calculate tooth to interesting
things we calculated the energy we could
calculate the number of photons let's
say let's think about the number of
photons let's go back to the harmonic
oscillator what do we find we found that
the energy of a single harmonic
oscillator was h-bar Omega
I think divided by e to the beta H bar
Omega minus 1 is that correct that's the
energy okay now each oscillator each
quantum of the oscillator has an energy
equal to H bar Omega right H bar Omega
is the energy of each quantum of
oscillation let's use the term that we
now use h-bar Omega is the energy of
each photon in oscillation of the
electromagnetic field so this is the
energy if I divide it by H bar Omega it
will give me the number of quanta so
let's divide it by H bar Omega the
number of photons in each mode of
oscillation let's call it in Omega
is e to the beta H bar Omega Obon minus
one okay now you can take all of the
modes of oscillation and add up all of
the photons it's a similar integral the
only difference is that it doesn't have
the H bar you know the the numerator
here almost the identical integral a
little bit different you can calculate
the number of photons that's not so hard
to do and you can calculate the entropy
how do we calculate the entropy we use
the statistical mechanics that we've
we've calculated the three energy let's
say anybody remember the formula for
relating energy entropy and free energy
e minus TS a is e minus TS right a is
equal a is equal to e minus TS so s is
equal to a minus e now II minus a
divided by T well we've calculated the
energy we calculated the energy we
calculated the free energy they were
proportional to each other except for a
factor one third right that's what went
on here
the energy and the free energy differed
by a factor of two thirds so the energy
minus the free energy is going to be
basically two thirds of something it's
what's going to be two thirds of the
energy and the energy is proportional to
t to the fourth times sigma times of
Stefan Boltzmann constant so T to the
fourth times Sigma is the numerator
divided by T so T cubed times the Stefan
Boltzmann constant or something like
that is the number of photons sorry is
the entropy if you work it out you'll
find out
that it's essentially equal to the
number of photons the total number of
photons the total number of photons the
numerical constant distinguishes them
this number here if you work it out is
basically the same as the integral let's
just look at it for a moment supposing I
wanted to count the total number of
photons here's the number of photons at
a given frequency it would be integral
the same integral that we did before
exactly the same integral we did before
what was it decay ah K H Bar K H bar
what Omega no Omega K H Bar C e to the K
H bar C minus 1 that was the end that
was the integral that we did before to
calculate the energy D 3 K all right ok
we did that integral but now we have a
different integral it differs by not
having Omega in the numerator it's
exactly the same integral except this
factor is no longer there when
calculating the number of photons the
result is going to be incidentally do
you not do do you know where the 1 no 1
over beta to the 4th came from it came
from changing variables it came from the
four powers of K in the numerator when
we changed variables we said that U is
equal to the beta here beta H Bar C
times K so in the change of variables
between K and you there are 4 powers of
K in the numerator D 3 K times K that
gave us a 1 over beta to the fourth in
the integral without this we're just
going to get 1 over beta cubed which is
temperature cubed so the number of
photons will be proportional to the
entropy
that's a nice thing what it says is that
the total entropy at any temperature is
essentially the same as the total number
of photons one bit of information if you
like for each photon it's not one some
of the miracle number but the entropy
and number of photons are linearly
proportional to each other so entropy in
thermal equilibrium counts number of
photons in the radiation you can work
that out it's a nice integral to do you
work out the integral associated with
the with the number of photons and
compared with the entropy and that will
give you the entropy per photon if you
like the entropy per photon in the
thermal radiation and you know it's not
temperature dependent it's just some
number which I don't remember that PI's
and other things yeah I think it's a
nasty integral you can't do the integral
but you can express it in terms of
Riemann zeta-function x' but it's a
number okay
yes yes of electrons with one no only at
very high temperatures would that be
true take take the case of low
temperatures at very very low
temperatures the electron gas freezes
into a non-pro solid freezes into a well
it freezes into a ground state some
ground state are where every electron
occupies its own special state because
of the Pauli exclusion principle and it
has zero entropy so no it's not true
that that entropy is equal to the number
of electrons no it's rather special to
this system is the zero energy is not
zero on the system
sit again because the zero energy isn't
zero on the system zero energy isn't
zero that's not the reason that's not
the reason um as you remove heat from a
box of radiation you decrease the number
of photons but both times are not
conserved and cooling the box of gas
just eliminates removes photons from it
so as you cool it down towards its
ground state and eventually when you get
down to very very low temperatures there
are no photons left so the number of
photons and the entropy both go to zero
in the ground state for a system of
electrons electrons are conserved you
start taking out the energy from them
the electrons don't go away so if you
cool a system of electrons down to zero
temperature there's a lot of electrons
but no entropy so the entropy can't be
equal to the the the number of electrons
but photons are not conserved and as you
cool it the photons are just them
eliminated
they are absorbed into the walls okay
any other questions let's not throw home
a little bit early for more please visit
us at stanford.edu